<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>The Notenik Blog</title>
  <subtitle>The latest news about the Notenik Project</subtitle>
  <link href="https://notenik.net/atom.xml" type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://notenik.net/" type="text/html" rel="alternate"  />
  <updated>2021-05-22</updated>
  <rights>Copyright © 2021, Herb Bowie</rights>
  <author>
    <name>Herb Bowie</name>
  </author>
  <id>https://hbowie.net/atom.xml</id>
	<entry>
	  <title>Summary of Latest Features Added - 6.0.0 Edition</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.net/blog/summary-of-latest-features-added-6.0.0-edition.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.net/blog/summary-of-latest-features-added-6.0.0-edition.html</id>
	  <published>2021-05-14T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-05-14T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
	  	<p>Version 6.0.0 has just been released to the Mac App Store, so perhaps it&apos;s time once again to summarize the new features that have been added to Notenik over the last few months. </p>

	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
	  	<![CDATA[
	  	<p>Version 6.0.0 has just been released to the Mac App Store, so perhaps it&apos;s time once again to summarize the new features that have been added to Notenik over the last few months. </p>
<p>First of all, additional options for customizing the Display tab have been added. You can still enter custom CSS via the Display Prefs (and these will now be retained reliably), but you can also supply an external display.css file for a Collection, and even a display.html file that uses a Notenik Merge template to allow full customization of the placement and appearance of fields on the Display tab. </p>
<p>Authors who publish on Medium can now post a draft directly to that platform from within Notenik. </p>
<p>Code fencing is now supported by the Notenik Markdown parser. </p>
<p>The List tab now has a contextual menu that allows a few convenient options for a selected Note. </p>
<p>Field naming and typing have been made more independent. In other words, you can now, for example, change the name of the Title field for a Collection, and still have it retain all the properties of the Title field. </p>
<p>When viewing a Note in the Display tab, you should now be able to use the Contextual Menu for any Link and select &apos;Open Link in New Window&hellip;&apos; in order to open that link in your preferred Web browser (instead of opening within the Notenik window). </p>
<p>If you decide to change the file extension for a Collection, by entering a new one in the Collection Prefs window, all Notes in that collection will be renamed to use the new extension. </p>
<p>For those who just wish to quickly create a new Collection within the iCloud Notenik folder, there&apos;s now a streamlined way of doing that. </p>
<p>File attachments can now be added via drag-and-drop on a Note displayed on the List tab. </p>
<p>When you open a Collection, Notenik will now reposition you on the last Note selected the last time the Collection was opened. </p>
<p>For use in website generation, a special &apos;Minutes to Read&apos; field type has been added, as well as an &apos;Image Name&apos; field. Both of these fields will be populated automatically. </p>
<p>Each Collection can now be assigned its own shortcut string, and such Collections can now be easily opened through the new Quick Action window. You can also use this new window to quickly create a new Note, or add body text to an existing one. </p>

	  	]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Using Notenik in Some Trendy, Cool Ways</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.net/blog/using-notenik-in-some-trendy-cool-ways.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.net/blog/using-notenik-in-some-trendy-cool-ways.html</id>
	  <published>2021-02-12T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-02-12T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
	  	<p>A Digital Commonplace Book? A Personal Knowledge Management System? A <em>Zettelkasten</em>? How are all these things related to one another, and how can Notenik help? </p>

	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
	  	<![CDATA[
	  	<p>In the last week or so I&apos;ve come across a couple of articles touting some trendy ways for individuals to collect information that is personally meaningful to them. </p>
<p>First, there was this <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/02/10/technology/personaltech/make-digital-commonplace-book.html"><em>New York Times</em> piece by J. D. Biersdorfer</a> telling you how to &quot;Create a Digital Commonplace Book.&quot; </p>
<p>Then there was a <a href="https://thesweetsetup.com/pkm-intro-for-creatives/">blog post at <em>The Sweet Setup</em></a> offering a &quot;PKM Primer: An Introduction to Personal Knowledge Management for Creatives.&quot; </p>
<p>Both pieces were well done, and I encourage you to read the pair. </p>
<p>A <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commonplace_book">commonplace book</a>, it turns out, is &quot;a book into which notable extracts from other works are copied for personal use,&quot; according to the <em>New Oxford American Dictionary</em>.  </p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personal_knowledge_management">Personal Knowledge Management</a> is a bit harder to define in a way that is both concise and enlightening. But if you just conjoin the ordinary meanings of the three constituent words, you&apos;ll get the general drift. </p>
<p>And then there&apos;s the whole <a href="https://eugeneyan.com/writing/note-taking-zettelkasten/"><em>Zettelkasten</em> movement</a>, in case I haven&apos;t slung enough exotic terms around yet. </p>
<p>But while these are theoretically separate topics, I think they are all attempts to address some common problems for anyone interested in constructive thinking. </p>
<p>Consider: </p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>If we read/watch/listen broadly, and with intention, then we turn our attention successively to many sources of information. This seems a particular problem today, with so many digital sources of information clamoring for our attention (but then it turns out that people have been keeping commonplace books for centuries).   </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Some of the information we encounter is immediately useful &#8211; and some seems perfectly useless. Of what remains, some may be easily retrievable from the original (or an equivalent) source when needed. But once we eliminate this sort of detritus, then there are some few nuggets left that seem worth capturing, both because they appear to have some likely future value, and because they appear to be difficult to rediscover or recreate when needed.  </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>These nuggets judged to be worth keeping may be of three different sorts: </p>
<ul>
<li>Pure facts and information; </li>
<li>Interesting ideas; </li>
<li>Quotations &#8211; generally pithy expressions that are worth hanging onto because they express some meaningful idea in a particularly forceful and/or memorable fashion. </li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>If we simply jot down these nuggets, and then toss them onto a growing pile of similar notes, then it is unlikely that we will be able to find what is needed when it is needed.  </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>It follows, then, that if something is worth capturing at all in this manner, it is worth spending a little time on, in order to usefully categorize it, and perhaps connect it to other related bits of info. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Ideally, then, your collection of notes is something you usefully refer to in the future. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>And equally ideally, the value derived from your collection comes not only from the various notes, considered individually, but from the growing connections between them, as you build your collection over time. </p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Now of course there are many computerized tools available to you today that you can use to keep a digital commonplace book, and/or a personal knowledge management system, and/or a <em>zettelkasten</em>. And each of them has their own selling points, and there is certainly no one solution that will work equally well for everyone. </p>
<p>However&hellip; </p>
<p>Ahem&hellip; </p>
<p>I am here today to modestly commend to you my own little app, <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/notenik/id1465997984">Notenik</a>, to be used for these purposes. </p>
<p>I&apos;ve been working on Notenik, or one of its predecessor apps, for about fifteen years. </p>
<p>And I&apos;ve been using these apps to create my own commonplace book (although I didn&apos;t always know it was called that) for most of this time. </p>
<p>How valuable have I found it to create notes in this way? </p>
<p>Well, I&apos;ve created a number of different collections of notes over the years, and some have proven to be of more enduring value than others. </p>
<p>But today I can point to three different published works that grew directly out of my own penchant for collecting ideas and quotations in this fashion. </p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.reasontorock.com">Reason To Rock</a> &#8211; A book about rock music that describes it in terms of an artistic movement. </li>
<li><a href="https://www.softdevbigideas.com">Big Ideas in Software Development</a> &#8211; A compendium of the biggest and most important ideas useful to software developers. </li>
<li><a href="https://practopian.org/core/index.html">The Practical Utopian</a> &#8211; An evolving collection of writings about philosophy and culture. </li>
</ul>
<p>Now why do I use Notenik for this purpose, instead of some other tool? </p>
<ol>
<li>I can create as many different collections of notes as I wish. </li>
<li>Within each collection I can give each note as many different tags, and sub-tags, as I wish. </li>
<li>Each note can link to other notes. </li>
<li>I can format the body of each note using Markdown &#8211; which can in turn be converted to HTML when needed. </li>
<li>Each collection can have a different set of fields associated with each note. </li>
<li>I can sort and filter my notes using the available fields. </li>
<li>I can get my information out of Notenik in a whole variety of useful ways. </li>
<li>My notes are stored in plain text files on my personal computer, so I know that I will retain access to all of them over a period of years and decades, without reliance on proprietary data formats or third-party software and services. </li>
<li>I can access and edit my notes using any text editor, in addition to Notenik. </li>
<li>I can backup and sync my notes using any tools and services I choose. </li>
<li>I don&apos;t want or need a tool that has a whole lot of graphic bells and whistles. All of the stuff I&apos;m interested in &#8211; quotations, ideas and information &#8211; is best captured using text. And the form in which it can most usefully be used is also text. So while taking a photo of a book page and stashing it into a digital notebook may feel cool, I am not convinced that such a practice is terribly useful. </li>
<li>I like having one tool that I can use for many different types of information. I want to focus on the information worth collecting, and the uses to which I can put such information &#8211; without being distracted by needing to focus on the tool(s) themselves. </li>
</ol>
<p>Now of course there is one strong reason why you might not want to give Notenik a try &#8211; it&apos;s only available on the Mac. So if you are a devout user of Windows, or Linux, and/or Android, or if you are convinced you need to perform your personal knowledge management on your iPad or iPhone, then you will have to consider some other tool. </p>
<p>On the other hand, though: </p>
<ul>
<li>If you don&apos;t currently own a Mac, <a href="https://www.tomsguide.com/reviews/macbook-air-2020-m1">now is an awfully good time to get one</a>. </li>
<li>If you&apos;re interested in practicing serious PKM, or in doing any serious constructive thinking, it&apos;s still really hard to beat a good laptop with a keyboard and a trackpad or mouse. </li>
</ul>
<p>That being said, Notenik is free and open-source (so I don&apos;t make any money off of it), and I&apos;m really more motivated to urge you to consider the practices we&apos;re discussing today, than I am to persuade you to use my own app. </p>
<p>After all, the more constructive thinking we have going on in our society, the better off we&apos;ll all be.  </p>

	  	]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>New Info on Fields and Labels</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.net/blog/new-info-on-fields-and-labels.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.net/blog/new-info-on-fields-and-labels.html</id>
	  <published>2021-02-03T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-02-03T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
	  	<p>There&apos;s a new Articles section on the website, and a new article on Notenik Fields and Labels that explains how to take full advantage of some of the latest changes to Notenik. </p>

	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
	  	<![CDATA[
	  	<p>There&apos;s quite a lot of Notenik news to talk about. </p>
<p>First of all, there&apos;s a new version, 5.5.0, that&apos;s just been released. As always, you can find the latest release in the <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/notenik/id1465997984">Mac App Store</a>. </p>
<p>There are one or two new convenience features in this release, but the bulk of the changes are going on behind the scenes. </p>
<p>In particular, the Notenik internals have been properly sorted to allow for pretty much any of the usual fields to be renamed. </p>
<p>So, if for one of your Collections, it would make more sense if the <code>Title</code> field were called the <code>Name</code> field, let&apos;s say, you can now make that happen by editing the <code>template</code> file for that Collection, changing <code>Title</code> to <code>Name</code>, and then adding <code>: &amp;lt;title&amp;gt;</code> after the label at the top of the <code>template</code> file, to tell Notenik to treat it as a <code>title</code> field, even though it&apos;s now called <code>Name</code>. </p>
<p>All of this needs a lot more space for a complete explanation. Rather than making the User Guide even longer by tucking all the details in there, I&apos;ve added an <a href="../articles.html">Articles</a> section to the <a href="https://notenik.net">website</a>, where you can now find a new article completely addressing the issue of <a href="../articles/field-labels-and-types.html">Field Labels and Types</a>. </p>
<p>If none of this sounds of interest to you, then of course you can just continue on using Notenik the way you&apos;ve been using it, without any concerns. </p>
<p>As always, if you do see anything about the app that you think needs a change, just <a href="mailto:support@notenik.net">drop me a line</a>. </p>

	  	]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik Turns the Big Five-O!</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.net/blog/notenik-turns-the-big-five-o.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.net/blog/notenik-turns-the-big-five-o.html</id>
	  <published>2020-12-10T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2020-12-10T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
	  	<p>Yes, that&apos;s right &#8211; Notenik version 5.0.0 has just been released, in all likelihood closing the books on 2020. So this feels like a good time to take a breather and look back on the path we&apos;ve traveled, along with new routes yet to explore. </p>

	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
	  	<![CDATA[
	  	<p>Yes, that&apos;s right &#8211; <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/notenik/id1465997984?mt=12">Notenik version 5.0.0 has just been released</a>, in all likelihood closing the books on 2020. So this feels like a good time to take a breather and look back on the path we&apos;ve traveled, along with new routes yet to explore. </p>
<p>I started work on the current version of Notenik &#8211; written in Swift, specifically for macOS &#8211; in January of 2019. </p>
<p>Version 1.0.0 was released in the Mac App Store in June of that same year. </p>
<p>After the initial release, I fell into a routine of advancing the version number by 0.1.0 with each update (except for a handful of emergency fixes that exercised that third digit). </p>
<p>So that means 40 significant releases in the last year and a half, for an average of one new release every two weeks or so &#8211; which feels like a pretty good clip! </p>
<p>That first version started out with the ability to manage one or more collections of notes &#8211; with each note containing one or more fields &#8211; and to present lists of notes as well as an outline view organized by tags. </p>
<p>In addition to a continual stream of minor refinements, the following significant capabilities have been added along the way: </p>
<ul>
<li>Maintaining a collection of web bookmarks, with the ability to generate a Favorites page in HTML; </li>
<li>Adding file attachments to notes; </li>
<li>Merging note information into templates to generate HTML pages, and scripting to sort and filter notes, and pump them through a series of templates. </li>
<li>Various refinements for handling custom field types, such as Date, Recurs and Seq. </li>
<li>Adjustments to handle folders full of text files not originally created by, nor intended for use with, Notenik; </li>
<li>Creation of a custom Markdown parser for use by Notenik; </li>
<li>Support for wiki-style links between Notes; </li>
<li>Support for bookmarks, citations, and tables of contents &#8211; all extensions to the original Markdown syntax. </li>
</ul>
<p>I&apos;ve had email correspondence with a number of Notenik users, all making enlightening suggestions about how the app could be improved or expanded in a variety of ways, and I&apos;ve been able to implement <a href="https://notenik.net/issues.html">about 80% of these ideas</a>, usually within a week or two. </p>
<p>Notenik&apos;s rating in the <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/notenik/id1465997984?mt=12">App Store</a> now stands at 4.9 (out of 5), based on submissions from 17 users. Five users have submitted reviews, all of them with positive comments. </p>
<p>All of this has been a labor of love &#8211; I charge nothing for Notenik, the code is all <a href="https://github.com/hbowie/notenik-swift">open-source</a>, and I collect no data from users. But during the last couple of years, and 2020 in particular, I&apos;ve been grateful for a retirement project that allows me to turn away from the television, the news feed, the social media chatter, and the email, and permits me to focus on building something tangible that I and others can use. It&apos;s a great joy. </p>
<p>So what&apos;s in the queue for 2021? </p>
<p>It would be great to get some broader exposure for Notenik. In particular, some sort of published third-party review of the app would be really helpful in getting the word out to potential users. </p>
<p>And then there&apos;s more code to write. At some point I&apos;d like to get an iOS version of Notenik out there. And a version that runs on a Web server would also be intriguing. But then, just when I think I&apos;m done for a while, there&apos;s yet another feature to add to the existing macOS app. </p>
<p>There&apos;s more fun to be had, for sure. <a href="https://notenik.net/rss.xml">Stay tuned</a>, and climb on board to be part of the journey! </p>

	  	]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Current Best Practices for Notenik Web Generation</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.net/blog/current-best-practices-for-notenik-web-generation.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.net/blog/current-best-practices-for-notenik-web-generation.html</id>
	  <published>2020-11-30T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2020-11-30T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
	  	<p>My current recommendations for those just starting to use Notenik to generate a website. </p>

	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
	  	<![CDATA[
	  	<p>One of the many things that <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/notenik/id1465997984?mt=12">Notenik</a> can be used for is website generation. </p>
<p>I&apos;ve set this up in many different ways over the years, for a number of different sites that I have authored. </p>
<p>If you&apos;d like to know more about the evolution of my thinking in this regard, you might want to take a look at this <a href="evolving-use-of-notenik-for-web-generation.html">previous post</a>. </p>
<p>But if you&apos;d just like to cut to the chase, and learn what I would consider current best practices, then this post is for you. (In any case, though, come back here if you decide to take a detour to read the history lesson.) </p>
<h2 id="folder-structure">Folder Structure</h2>
<p>Let me start by explaining the recommended folder structure. </p>
<p>The top level folder should be given whatever name is meaningful to you. This entire folder can then be put under version control using <a href="https://git-scm.com">git</a>, and uploaded to <a href="https://github.com">GitHub</a>, or any other online repository you happen to be using. The entire contents of this folder can then be uploaded to your web server, or web hosting service, using your preferred FTP software. (I use <a href="https://www.git-tower.com/mac">Tower</a> and <a href="https://panic.com/transmit/">Transmit</a> for these chores, respectively.) </p>
<p>This top level folder will eventually hold all of your html files, which will have been generated using Notenik. It will initially be empty, except for&hellip; </p>
<p>A subfolder named <strong>notes</strong> will then contain all of your actual Notes that are normally maintained by Notenik. Each note is stored in a plain text file, and contains a page of content, along with suitable metadata about that content. </p>
<p>A subfolder named <strong>files</strong> may exist within the <code>notes</code> folder. This folder would contain any note attachments, potentially including image files (jpeg or png files, for example). </p>
<p>A subfolder named <strong>mirror</strong> should be nested within the <code>notes</code> folder. This folder would then contain whatever files are used to <em>mirror</em> the content from the Notenik format to the final html format found in the top folder. </p>
<p>The following subfolders would then be placed within the <code>mirror</code> folder. </p>
<p>The <strong>css</strong> folder would be used to store any cascading stylesheet files. </p>
<p>An <strong>includes</strong> folder can be used for any chunks of html to be included from one or more template files. </p>
<p>A <strong>scripts</strong> folder can be used for any Notenik scripting files to be run. </p>
<p>A <strong>templates</strong> folder would be used for the various templates that would be used to convert your notes to html. </p>
<p>And that&apos;s it for the standard folder structure. Other subfolders may of course be added as needed, depending on the nature of your site. </p>
<h2 id="notenik-features">Notenik Features</h2>
<p>Notenik has a number of features that have been provided to facilitate website generation using the folder structure described above. </p>
<p>If you&apos;re starting from scratch, then you can use the <strong>New Web Collection</strong> command beneath the <code>Files</code> menu to create a new set of folders organized in this way. </p>
<p>If you have an existing Collection, then you can use the <strong>Stash Notes in Subfolder</strong> command beneath the <code>Transform</code> menu to reorganize your existing Collection, moving your existing Notes and subfolders into a new subfolder named <code>notes</code>. </p>
<p>In either case, when you go to open the Web Collection at a later date, simply use the normal <strong>Open</strong> command beneath the <code>File</code> menu, being sure to select the top-level folder &#8211; the one above the <code>notes</code> subfolder. In this way, Notenik will have the permissions it needs to write web pages into that top-level folder. </p>
<p>If you used the first command discussed above, to start from scratch, then your Collection will already contain a sample <code>mirror</code> folder. Otherwise, use the <strong>Generate Sample Mirror Folder</strong> command beneath the <code>Transform</code> menu to create some sample files and folders for mirroring. Feel free to modify these to suit your needs. </p>
<p>However you create it, if your Notenik collection has a subfolder named <code>mirror</code>, which in turn contains another folder named <code>templates</code>, which in turn contains a file whose name is something like <strong>note_mirror.html</strong> (containing both the word <code>note</code> and the word <code>mirror</code>), then that template file will be run every time you update one of your notes. And if that template file is set up to write to a location three levels above its location, then you will end up having a webpage created for each Note in your collection, and each webpage will be kept up-to-date as you make changes to your Collection. </p>
<p>If your <code>templates</code> folder also contains a file whose name is something like <strong>index_mirror.html</strong>, then that file will be run whenever you request indexing from a command beneath the <code>Transform</code> menu. Alternatively, if you select that option as part of the Collection Preferences, the index will be regenerated every time any page in the collection is updated. </p>
<p>And if you&apos;d like to visit the generated <strong>index.html</strong> page in your Web browser, then you can select <strong>Browse Web Index</strong> beneath the <code>Transform</code> menu. </p>
<h2 id="file-formats">File Formats</h2>
<p>For further info: </p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><a href="https://notenik.net/template-spec.html">The Template File Spec</a> - Template files are used to merge the data from your Notes into a standard page template for your website. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://notenik.net/script-spec.html">The Scripting File Spec</a> - Scripts can be used to sort and filter the data from your Notes, as well as pumping the resulting data through your template files. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://notenik.net/swift.html">The Notenik User Guide</a> - For all other details about Notenik. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://notenik.net/blog.html">The Notenik Blog</a> - Including tutorials and background info about Notenik. </p>
</li>
</ul>

	  	]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Evolving Use of Notenik for Web Generation</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.net/blog/evolving-use-of-notenik-for-web-generation.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.net/blog/evolving-use-of-notenik-for-web-generation.html</id>
	  <published>2020-11-30T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2020-11-30T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
	  	<p>Some history about how my latest thinking has evolved. </p>

	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
	  	<![CDATA[
	  	<p>I&apos;ve been using <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/notenik/id1465997984?mt=12">Notenik written in Swift for the Mac</a>, or one of its predecessors (Notenik written in Java, or PSTextMerge before that, or TDF Czar before that) to generate my websites (starting with <a href="https://www.reasontorock.com">ReasonToRock.com</a>) for almost 20 years. </p>
<p>For almost all of that time, I&apos;ve used a homegrown <a href="https://notenik.net/script-spec.html">scripting language</a>, and a homegrown <a href="https://notenik.net/template-spec.html">templating language</a>, to generate those sites from some sort of separate data source: tab-delimited files, to start with. </p>
<p>Over this time, my thoughts about the data source and its relationship to the final website, as well as the script and template files used to convert one to the other, have evolved gradually, coming to some sort of conclusion, I think, with the <a href="https://notenik.net/swift.html#version-history">4.9.0 release of Notenik</a>. </p>
<p>Let me briefly note the steps in this evolution, before explaining my latest thoughts. </p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>I originally used <a href="https://textile-lang.com">Textile</a> formatting for my content, but switched to <a href="https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">Markdown</a> after Reason to Rock. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I moved my primary data source(s) from some sort of tab-delimited file to a collection of text files in the <a href="https://notenik.net/blog/the-thinking-behind-the-notenik-file-format.html">Notenik format</a>. Each Note, then, contains a piece of content, as well as metadata about that content. And both can be edited using Notenik, or any text editor available for macOS. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I originally placed my content and my metadata and my scripts and templates in various folders that were separate from the resulting website, or perhaps sat alongside the resulting site. I eventually realized a couple of problems with this arrangement: a) the whole kit and caboodle was not as portable as it might have been, since the source files were not stored together with the generated html files; and b) with recent changes in macOS security, Notenik would end up reading data from one folder that it had been granted access to, but then trying to write to a different folder, to which it did not have access. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>All of my html generation was originally triggered manually, when I explicitly told Notenik to run a script that I had recorded/written. I eventually realized, though, that it might be better to update the corresponding html page of content whenever the original Notenik page was updated. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I briefly flirted with the idea of having Notenik mirror each Note to a corresponding html page that would sit in the same folder. After seeing the results, though, I realized that this was a bit messy. </p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>And so, with the 4.9.0 release of Notenik I&apos;ve added some new features that seem to resolve the latest set of issues. </p>
<p>However, nothing that worked before has been broken or disabled. In fact, my various websites still use all of the things listed above that I have decided to move away from, and Notenik still works to regenerate all of those sites whenever I have the need to do so. </p>
<p>For anyone coming to Notenik for the first time, though, I&apos;d like to explain what I would consider current best practices for using Notenik to generate web pages and sites. </p>
<p>And that is the topic for the <a href="current-best-practices-for-notenik-web-generation.html">next post</a>. </p>

	  	]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Additional Updates to Notenik - November 4, 2020</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.net/blog/additional-updates-to-notenik-november-4-2020.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.net/blog/additional-updates-to-notenik-november-4-2020.html</id>
	  <published>2020-11-04T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2020-11-04T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
	  	<p>I&apos;ve made a bunch of Notenik improvements since my last blog post, and I attempt to summarize them here. </p>

	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
	  	<![CDATA[
	  	<p>Well, we&apos;ve had a bunch of updates to Notenik since my last blog post, so let me try to hit the high points here. Some of these were attempts to scratch itches that I was feeling, while others were implemented in response to requests/suggestions from other users. In addition to the list below, there were several minor tweaks to improve the user experience. </p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Notenik now has its own iCloud container, which means that Collections stored at this location can be more easily accessed, either through an Open from iCloud option beneath the File menu, or from the new Navigation Board. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>A Navigation board can be opened from a new option beneath the File menu. It will also appear when you close the last open Collection without quitting. This window allows easy opening of recently opened Collections, as well as Collections stored in Notenik&apos;s iCloud container. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Added some drag and drop support. Users can now drag a bookmark from the URL field at the top of a browser window and drop it anywhere on the list view of a Collection to add the bookmark as a new Note. You can also drag a Note from one Collection to another. Contacts and Emails can also be imported in very basic ways. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Duplicates are now treated differently &#8211; Notenik will simply append a sequence number and allow the duplicate title to be added to the Collection. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Double-clicking a Note from the List tab will now attempt to launch whatever Link the Note may have. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>A new command beneath the Note menu will discard any edits currently in work. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Another new command beneath the Note menu will increment the major portion of a two-part Seq field instead of the minor portion. As an example, incrementing &apos;1.00&apos; would result in a new value of &apos;2.00&apos;, instead of &apos;1.01&apos;. Any subsequent values that would result in duplicates will also be incremented. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Added a couple of Collection preferences that allow the Display of a Note to be altered slightly. One option will do away with an explicit Body field label in the Note display; the other option will display a Note&apos;s title as a level 1 heading. Both options may be valuable for Collections of Notes that are primarily intended to be viewed as documents. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Internal wiki-style links between Notes have been enhanced so that timestamps will be used to prevent links from breaking if link targets are renamed. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Notenik&apos;s own Markdown parser has been refined. Several bugs have been fixed. An option to automatically generate a Table of Contents has been added, along with support for Multimarkdown-style footnotes. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>A new Counts window is available, which will show character, line and word counts for the currently selected Note. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>A new Sort option is available, to sort by Tags. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Added new keyboard shortcuts for status updates. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Users can now specify a &apos;pick-from&apos; field type in a template file, and specify the allowable values. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Users can also specify a Boolean format for a custom field, with the field being represented by a checkbox on the Edit tab. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Added new Note sharing options for formatting a Note as a Quotation, in either Markdown or HTML. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Added an import option for XML that will allow users of iWisdom to import their collections of quotations into Notenik (since iWisdom is no longer supported). </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>For those interested in the code, the monolithic Notenik project was refactored to break out several reusable packages: NotenikUtils, for the most general-purpose utilities; NotenikMkdown, for the internal Markdown parser; NotenikTextile, for the beginnings of a rudimentary Textile parser; and NotenikLib, for Notenik code that might be reused on platforms other than the Mac. </p>
</li>
</ul>

	  	]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Recent Updates to Notenik - March, 2020</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.net/blog/recent-updates-to-notenik-march-2020.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.net/blog/recent-updates-to-notenik-march-2020.html</id>
	  <published>2020-03-25T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2020-03-25T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
	  	<p>A summary of notable changes to the Mac App since December, 2019. </p>

	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
	  	<![CDATA[
	  	<p>There have been a few version releases since I last wrote about recent changes in the <a href="https://notenik.net/blog.html">blog</a> back in December, so let me hit on some of the more significant recent developments. </p>
<ul>
<li>The most recent release, 3.2.0, added a new internal Markdown parser as a third alternative, in addition to <a href="https://github.com/iwasrobbed/Down">Down</a> and <a href="https://github.com/JohnSundell/Ink">Ink</a>. It&apos;s probably not quite perfect, but I tried to stick as close as possible to John Gruber&apos;s documentation of the functionality intended for both <a href="https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax">Markdown</a> and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/projects/smartypants/">SmartyPants</a>, and it seems to be working pretty well for me. The main improvement here is better handling of wiki-style inter-note links. These are now only available when using the internal parser, but no longer require you to specifically request this feature: it&apos;s just built in to the new parser. See the Application Preferences to select the new parser. </li>
<li>Added the ability to mirror a Collection of Notes to an alternate format &#8211; most usefully, HTML. This new ability makes it super easy to generate a simple website that anyone can access with a Web browser. Once you set this up, the HTML mirror copies are automatically kept up-to-date for you in the background, as you go about working on the text files within Notenik. See the new Transform menu for commands to help you set this up. </li>
<li>The Edit view is now scrollable, in case the number of fields in a Collection is too large to fit in the available space for the window. </li>
<li>The Collection Preferences window was redesigned to make it more usable. </li>
<li>Notenik is now available in the App Store for users still on High Sierra. </li>
<li>Made a few usability improvements, including the addition of the day of week name next to the date on a Note&apos;s display view, and the addition of the letter &apos;T&apos; in the leftmost column in the List view to indicate Notes with dates of today. </li>
<li>A number of bugs have been fixed. </li>
<li>Restructured the User Guide to make it easer to use. </li>
</ul>
<p>As usual, see the Notenik <a href="https://notenik.net/swift.html#version-history">Version History</a> and the relevant sections of the <a href="https://notenik.net/swift.html">User Guide</a> for further details.  And drop me a line at &lt;support@notenik.net&gt; if any problems or questions. </p>

	  	]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Using Notenik with Existing Text Files</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.net/blog/using-notenik-with-existing-text-files.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.net/blog/using-notenik-with-existing-text-files.html</id>
	  <published>2020-01-29T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2020-01-29T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
	  	<p>Since Notenik is rather late to the game of managing text files, and since those already using similar sorts of files are probably among those interested in my app, I wanted to talk a bit about how the latest version of Notenik can be used with existing folders full of text files. </p>

	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
	  	<![CDATA[
	  	<p>As I&apos;ve noted in another recent blog post, <a href="https://notenik.net/blog/the-thinking-behind-the-notenik-file-format.html">Notenik uses its own unique file format</a>. However, since Notenik is rather late to the game of managing text files, and since those already using similar sorts of files are probably among those interested in my app, I wanted to talk a bit about how the latest version of Notenik can be used with existing folders full of text files. The information provided below includes a number of updates made starting with version 2.6.0 and continuing through 2.9.0. </p>
<p>First, philosophically, Notenik tries to follow <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robustness_principle">Postel&apos;s Law</a>: </p>
<p>&gt; Be conservative in what you do, be liberal in what you accept from others. </p>
<p>Unfortunately, it is not possible for Notenik to be endlessly liberal in this regard, and there are certainly loosely formatted text files that may not be interpreted by Notenik according to the author&apos;s wishes. </p>
<h3 id="rules-for-reading">Rules for Reading</h3>
<p>With that being said, here are some rules that Notenik will try to apply to interpret existing text files in the best possible manner. (Many or even most of these rules involve recognition of the start of the note&apos;s body, even though the note lacks the explicit &apos;Body:&apos; field label found in the standard Notenik format.) </p>
<ol>
<li>Notenik will respect a template file that it finds, but it does not insist on the presence of a template file. </li>
<li>Notenik will place a file named &apos;- INFO.nnk&apos; in any folder that it opens successfully. Notenik uses this file to track some basic info about the Collection. Notenik also uses the presence of this file to indicate that the folder contains a Notenik Collection. </li>
<li>Notenik will generally respect whatever metadata tags are found at the top of the file, unless you have specified otherwise. In this respect, Notenik generally follows the same conventions as the <a href="https://fletcher.github.io/MultiMarkdown-4/metadata.html">MultiMarkdown Metadata</a> specification. </li>
<li>In accordance with this same spec, Notenik will respect a line of three dashes before and after the metadata, to indicate the start and end of the metadata block. The line after the metadata can also be one of four periods. </li>
<li>Notenik normally expects to see blank lines between metadata fields, for improved readability. However, if the first line contains a Title field, and is immediately followed by another metadata field, without an intervening blank line, then Notenik will assume that the first blank line encountered should end the metadata block and start the body of the note. </li>
<li>If a file does not begin with any metadata, but starts with a normal <a href="https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax#header">Markdown level 1 heading</a>, then Notenik will use the contents of that heading as the title of the note. </li>
<li>If a file does not start with either metadata or a Markdown level 1 heading, then Notenik will use the file name (dropping the file extension) as the title of the note, and use the entire contents of the file as the body. </li>
<li>If a file does not start with metadata, but does start with a Markdown level 1 heading, then the second line of the file may use a &apos;#&apos;, immediately followed by text (without any intervening spaces) to indicate that the text should be treated as tags for the note. I&apos;m not quite sure where this convention originated, or how many people use it, but there it is. </li>
</ol>
<h3 id="rules-for-updating">Rules for Updating</h3>
<p>When a note is updated, Notenik will generally try to respect each file&apos;s existing format, rather than rewriting the note using Notenik&apos;s format. </p>
<h3 id="rules-for-new-notes">Rules for New Notes</h3>
<p>New notes will be written out using Notenik&apos;s file format. </p>
<h3 id="converting-an-entire-collection">Converting an Entire Collection</h3>
<p>If you wish to convert an existing collection of files so that they all are consistently formatted using the standard Notenik format, then the best way to do this is to open your existing folder, review it to make sure that all or most of the data is being interpreted favorably, and then use the Export command beneath the File menu to export the collection into the Notenik format. This will create a new folder containing all of your notes, formatted in the Notenik format. </p>
<h3 id="backing-up">Backing Up</h3>
<p>Notenik is open-source software released under the terms of the <a href="https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT">MIT license</a>. I mention this only to emphasize the point that, although I&apos;ve done everything I can think of to enable Notenik to be used with existing folders full of text files, the software is provided &quot;As Is&quot;, without warranty of any kind. If you have problems, I&apos;d like to know about them, so I can hopefully further improve the software. But you should be careful to back up your existing data before using it with Notenik (and during, of course).  </p>
<h3 id="feedback">Feedback</h3>
<p>If you run into any problems with any of this, or have any suggestions for further improvements, please feel free to email me at <a href="mailto:support@notenik.net">support at notenik.net</a> and I&apos;ll see what I can do to help. </p>

	  	]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>The Thinking Behind the Notenik File Format</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.net/blog/the-thinking-behind-the-notenik-file-format.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.net/blog/the-thinking-behind-the-notenik-file-format.html</id>
	  <published>2020-01-10T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2020-01-10T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
	  	<p>People have been storing notes in text files long before Notenik came along. So why is the Notenik format different? </p>

	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
	  	<![CDATA[
	  	<p>People have been storing notes in text files long before Notenik came along. </p>
<p>At their most basic, such a note might consist simply of a chunk of text, with the file name serving as the note&apos;s title. </p>
<p>A slightly more sophisticated approach would be to use <a href="https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax">Markdown</a> to format a note, with a level 1 heading at the top of the file supplying a title for the note. </p>
<p>The use of <a href="https://fletcher.github.io/MultiMarkdown-4/metadata.html">MultiMarkdown metadata</a> adds even more possibilities, allowing multiple keys and associated values to be specified at the top of a file. </p>
<p>Although Notenik will read and respect all of these different sorts of text files, its own native format is a bit different from any of these. An example follows: </p>
<pre>
<code>Title: The Thinking Behind the Notenik File Format
</code></pre>
<pre>
<code>Tags: notenik, files
</code></pre>
<pre>
<code>Date: Jan 10, 2020
</code></pre>
<pre>
<code>Teaser:
</code></pre>
<pre>
<code>People have been storing notes in text files long before Notenik came along.
</code></pre>
<pre>
<code>Body:
</code></pre>
<pre>
<code>People have been storing notes in text files long before Notenik came along.
</code></pre>
<pre>
<code>At their most basic, such a note might consist simply of a chunk of text, with the file name serving as the note&amp;apos;s title.
</code></pre>
<p>The Notenik format is very similar to the MultiMarkdown metadata format, but differs in that an explicit Body label is expected to indicate the start of the Note&apos;s body, rather than the body being assumed to start after the first blank line, or three hyphens, or four periods. </p>
<p>So why is the Notenik format different? </p>
<p>The answer, in general, is that I wanted Notenik files to have a bit more flexibility than any of these other formats, without sacrificing any of their simplicity or readability. </p>
<p>So whereas these other formats are primarily for documents, with at most some ability to supply metadata describing the docs, a Notenik file is an object consisting of a number of fields, with one or more of those fields containing text formatted using Markdown. </p>
<p>That being said, a Notenik file is not a completely general-purpose object: it&apos;s not intended to compete with JSON, for example. For one thing, each note must have a Title field and a Body field, in addition to other fields. Also, each field generally consists of a single value, without any convention for handling arbitrary lists, or any nesting of objects. </p>
<p>So there you have it: a Notenik Note sits somewhere between a Markdown doc with metadata and a full-fledged  object with any number of complex fields. Which makes it simple enough to be read and written by ordinary humans using any text editor, and yet flexible enough to help such users keep track of any number of useful, everyday objects. </p>
<p>Which was exactly my intent when concocting this format. </p>

	  	]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
</feed>
